this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
I want to start talking about quantum
mechanics now we haven't talked about
quantum mechanics we've talked about
classical physics in a world where what
we can call the state space the space of
states is discrete we've talked about
hopping around from one state to another
and how information is counted in bits
how with time you can jump from one
state to another and so forth
that's all classical physics or it's
physics based on classical logic
classical logic means that the space
state is a boolean space so that
everybody know what a boolean space is
if not all it means is a bunch of points
in some space and that each point
represents a state and all of the logic
is classical logic classical logic that
Aristotle would have understood that the
Newton would have understood and so
forth
whereas quantum mechanics makes use of
an entirely new kind of logic which is
in a very basic way different to to
illustrate it I'd like to start with the
basic idea first of all of a single
quantum bit a qubit we talked about the
classical bit which is just the heads
tails type distinction here we can I
have my prop already this end is
different than this end if I point it up
that's one state if I point it down
that's another state that's the two
state system and that's all there is to
it nothing in between
assume nothing in between that's that's
the basic classical bit either up or
down with nothing in between ah and of
course you're gonna have many bits whoo
that's fun
you can have many bits to bits three
bits four bits whatever and pretty much
all the physics anything in physics can
be represented or at least approximated
by a system of of classical bits
anything in classical physics quantum
physics the concept of a bit is very
very different the concept of a bit of
information and that's what we want to
talk about today the basic simplest
example is the spin of an electron now
we don't have to know very much about
what spin means does it have something
to do with spinning or not this is not
very important what is important is that
every electron has associated with it a
vector now we're going to get into big
trouble because there are two things
that I'm going to wind up calling
vectors one of them is abstract vector
spaces which we're going to come to in a
little while and the other is vectors in
ordinary space a vector I did this I
took with me just to illustrate the idea
of a vector you know what a vector is in
ordinary space it's an object with a
length and a direction and I put a nail
in the end here to indicate the arrow so
that you'll know which way it's pointing
it's not pointing at me it's pointing up
in the corner of the room there that's
your naive elementary physics concept of
a vector a thing in ordinary space that
has a direction of course it also has
components for example this vector here
has a component in the horizontal
direction it has a component in the
vertical direction but altogether it's
pointing in in this other direction so
that's one concept of a vector a pointer
in space with a length in a and a
direction now there's another thing
we're going to call vectors which is a
more abstract concept and there's not
necessarily in general will not be
referring to things in space it's an
abstract mathematics it was a different
word for it we're going to be talking
about vector spaces I think sometimes
when I teach quantum mechanics I'm
up a new word for one or the other of
them call it a Schecter or something I
don't know but it never really works so
we have to keep in mind that when I use
the word vector sometimes maybe I should
just make in the word yeah that's a good
idea
let's just call this an arrow you know
how long I will last before I start
calling it a vector not very long okay
right now the spin of an electron is a
an arrow I was going to say vector I
can't help it no I cannot I can't do it
I'm going to call it a vector I'm going
to call it a vector I can't help myself
let's call a spatial vector how about a
spatial vector a special vector what
means one an ordinary space so if my
fist is the electron over here the
electron has attached to it
a mathematical vector it's not a rod
like this but it's a sense of
directionality really what it is the
direction of twist but just think of it
as every electron has attached to it a
vector which can point you might think
in any direction in space in fact in
some sense it can point in any direction
in space and in fact that vector can
also be thought of as a magnet it can be
thought of as a bar magnet with a North
Pole and a South Pole so here's the
North Pole with a nail the South Pole is
over here every electron is a little
magnet that's and the mag the amount the
strength of the magnet which is measured
in some units which I forget in what
they called strengthen magnet units is
some particular number so that means all
electrons there space vectors that go
with them the the it's called the
magnetic moment the magnetic moments are
all the same length they may point in
different directions but they're all the
same length and we can simply imagine
that that they are objects all of the
same length of a common length but
different directions now let's talk
about ordinary classical magnets and I
want to talk about the concept of
preparing the state and detecting a
state we're still thinking very
classically for the moment I know
everything I explained here was
completely with classical logic so
here's our electron and it has attached
to it an arrow with a North Pole and a
South Pole and let's say I want to
prepare that electron in a configuration
where its mat where its magnetic moment
this little vector is pointing this
North day it doesn't stay that doesn't
stand for its direction it stands for
the North Pole of the magnet I want to
have the North Pole I want the magnet to
be pointed vertically upward I want to
prepare it that way how do I do it okay
what you do is you simply create a large
magnetic field for example you put a you
create a magnet this is not a very good
pin you create a magnet you can do it as
an electromagnet if you like turn on
some current make an electromagnet or
the North Pole over here a South Pole
over here and the electron is supposed
to be in the magnetic field and what
will happen to that electron what will
happen to a little bar magnet
well what actually will happen to the
little bar magnet if you know anything
about how bar magnets move magnetic
fields is it will precess it will not
just jump up into our right position not
unless there's some friction instead
what it will do is it will process like
this around the magnetic field
everything imagine is in a vacuum so
there's no friction or anything like
that the electron will process around
like this that's what that's what a
little bar magnet would Daru but sooner
or later it will get rid of that
processional energy anybody know how it
gets rid of the processional energy it
radiates some radiation it radiates a
little bit of electromagnetic radiation
or a lot depending on the circumstances
and the size of the magnetic field and
so forth it will radiate away its energy
and come into the best energetic
configuration which is pointing straight
up where the North Pole of the magnet is
pointing toward the South Pole so where
the North Pole of the electron is
pointing toward the South Pole of the
magnet only which part of I've drawn
okay so that's the preparation and if we
do it with a very very big magnetic
field it will radiate that energy
quickly and very quickly come to
equilibrium with the North Pole of the
electron pointing vertically upward if
you like if we don't want to get I was
going to use the word entangled but
embroiled with the question of where the
electron is just imagine in your head
that I hold the electron absolutely
fixed in position so that the only thing
that can do anything interesting is the
is the direction of the magnetic field
okay so after a small amount of time
that that electron will be pointing in
the up direction we could if we liked we
could prepare the electron in the
different configuration by rotating the
magnetic poles to something like this
south north we could prepare the
electron initially so that it's pointing
in that direction okay so we start with
a electron pointing in some direction
now we want to measure we want to do a
measurement to find out which direction
this is this is a second kind of
experiment
it's the detection well first was the
preparation and then we do some things
to the electron whatever it is
and next we want to find out we want to
detect which direction the electron is
pointing in is it pointing in that
direction is it pointing in some other
direction mainly we could ask what's its
angle relative to the magnetic field and
to answer that question we do exactly
the same thing that we did to detect it
to prepare the electron we stick it into
the large magnetic field and wait for it
to radiate some radiation all right now
if this if all the physics were
classical and this were really a
perfectly classical setup a classical
love compass here instead of a quantum
mechanical electron then the again the
electron would eventually point its way
itself up but one measure of the angle
would be how much radiation it emits
ampel if it was almost perfectly upwards
to begin with if we're almost perfectly
upward then it only has a little bit of
extra energy perfectly upward has the
minimum energy when the North Pole is
pointing toward the South Pole that's
the minimum energy of that little
pointer here rotate it away a little bit
you give it a little bit of magnetic
energy and of course after you've put it
into them after you've let it come to
rest again it does so by giving off that
little bit of energy all right if you
were to go to a more extreme situation
where you pointed the electron in some
horizontally then by the time it got
vertical it would emit even more energy
finally if you pointed it straight down
it would emit the maximum amount of
energy in the form of radiation and so
you could measure at least the angle
relative to the magnetic field by
measuring how much radiation comes out
right and the answer would be a nice
newest function of the angle of the
electron so that when the answer when
the electron was pointing up no energy
comes out this is angle horizontally
energy emitted if the angle is zero
that's when it's pointing straight up no
energy if the angle is downward maximum
energy and then as you turn it over all
the ways back to zero energy and so
forth so you would measure then the same
way that you prepare you measure the
spin the spin direction of the electron
by letting it emit a photon by letting
it emit some radiation excuse me and
counting up the amount of the radiation
now I've told you completely the wrong
story for a real electron this is not
the way it works this is not the way it
works for a genuine electron something
else happens and I'll tell you now what
it is and it's very weird it really does
illustrate the weirdness of the quantum
world first of all no matter which way
you create the electron in here I won't
even try to give a classical picture if
I try to give a classical picture I will
prejudice the story you do something to
the electron and you put it over here
whatever you do to the electron one
thing you could do to the electron is
initially prepare it in some funny angle
but whatever you do to the electron you
put it over here you turn on the
magnetic field and one of two things
happens only two things can happen one
is it emits no photon no electromagnetic
radiation the other is that it emits one
quantum one photon of electromagnetic
radiation of a very particular frequency
it's the particular frequency that
corresponds to the energy of jumping
down the up whatever that energy is you
can emit a photon of just exactly that
energy and no other energy so there seem
to be it's almost as if the electron had
only two possible configurations you
jumble it up you don't know what you've
done to it you stick it in here and it
seems there's only two things that can
happen one is that it behaves as if it
were pointing up in which case it gives
off no photon the other is that it
behaves as if it were pointing downward
and gives off the photon and those are
the only two things that happen that can
happen all right but depending on exam
that seems a little weird
why because supposing you prepared the
electron by putting it into a magnetic
field that would have the effect of
freezing it into a direction let's say
at 45 degrees or even better at 90
degrees relative and lowest and reverse
horizontal then we would think to
ourselves well that electron is now
pointing in some other direction now
when I stick it into the vertical field
you would think that the response would
be something different then if it were
just plain up or down but no the
response is always just one of two
responses either it does give off a
photon or it doesn't and always of the
same energy so it seems that in some
sense there are only two states for the
electron either it's pointing up or it's
pointing down but wait a minute
what about if you put the electron into
a magnetic field pointing and yet a
different direction then you're going to
find that there are only two states for
the electron either pointing this way or
pointing that way something's very
confusing how many states does the
electron actually have is it only always
only up or down
or can you make it point in some other
direction and if you do make it point in
some other direction how come when you
stick it into the up/down detector here
the detector that detects the direction
in the up-down direction that you'll
only get two possibilities how come
there isn't the continuum of
possibilities in between that's the
puzzle or that's one of the puzzles of
quantum mechanics that it behaves as if
there are only two states up or down
when you measure it but you can
nevertheless prepare that electron
pointing in any direction by using a
magnetic field in the appropriate
direction now the one thing though that
is true is if you started with the
electron pointing upward let's suppose
we created the electron pointing upward
by putting it in this very strong
magnetic field shut off the magnetic
field for a while and then turn it back
on
the answer is we will get no Photon the
electron is pointing up supposing we
first create the electron in some other
direction pointing along the 45 degree
axis here and then we do the vertical
experiment we turn on the vertical
magnetic field we will either discover
that it's up or down but with a
probability distribution it will not be
definitely up or definitely down we can
do this experiment repeatedly over and
over and over many many times
identically sometimes we will find the
photon emitted sometimes we won't the
more the electron was initially pointing
vertically upward the less the
probability is that we will emit that
single photon the maximum probability
for emitting that photon will be if we
were originally pointing down somewhere
is in between the probability will be
1/2 for a photon to be emitted in fact
that's exactly the case
if the original electron were prepared
horizontally by a horizontal setup and
then put into the vertical field there
will be a probability of 1/2 that it
emits the photon and a half that it
doesn't emit the photon so there's
something extraordinary going on here in
some sense it seems there are only two
configurations
every time you measure that electron you
will either find it's up or it's down
nothing else nothing in between but
there are situations where it will be
probabilistically if you do the same
thing many many times you'll find as a
probability distribution and it's that
probability distribution R which has
some memory of which way you were
originally created the photon so a
quantum bit is a confusing thing it
looks like it has only two states up or
down but then you can make a point in
some other direction so that it looks
like there's other states possible again
when you measure it you find only two
possibilities it's a confusing entity a
quantum bit any questions so far
yeah Citian not that nothing my magnet
that's attached to an electron is it oh
yeah magnetic fields and pies all Chi on
you
one will try to do this the test and
create if you interacted with small
objects like other electrons like well
it field that's when we're going to
start to talk about entangled but let's
do one at a time and then we'll come to
the two electron system the two electron
system is the one that's really
interesting because that's where
entanglement starts to happen so let's
let's let's not try that one yet
little steps a little feet yeah quite a
question you have to do the whole
experiment over and over again prepared
if you want to give it experimentally
there's no way that with one experiment
that you can accumulate a probability
distribution okay prepare this right now
your turn the sealed off measure again
measure again where do you have to
prepare another prepare again each time
in between okay right right okay yes yes
yes you can prepare a lot of electrons
at once but but I think the question
goes something like this
supposing you prepared it this way and
then measured it and then measure the
same one again and then measure the same
in know once you discovered this was up
the first time it will be up every time
afterwards and so what you will discover
in the second experiment the third
experiment fourth experiment no photon
so once once the experiment has fixed it
to be up that's it
it has no memory anymore of this all
right
the other hand is yeah preparing means
waiting to see what happens in it when
it's it emits you assume yes brightening
is doing that again that's that's what
I'm cool that's one way of repair that's
one way of preparing an electron yeah
it's a usual way
I'm talking about electron by itself not
an atom yeah well I'm talking about an
electron perhaps which is in some
potential which nails it position down
so the Devonian we don't have to worry
about it moving we're just we're just
concentrating now purely on the spin of
the electron so imagine driving a nail
through the heart of the electron and
nailing it to the blackboard it still
has the ability for its spin to move to
the one electron Kosta is the electron
field to say c'est bien de Monday
yes Kosta is it cosmos time okay
well okay so is what we're imagine
imagining I want to do an experiment so
I take an electron which is there
originally I don't know how I got it
there anyway I like without the magnetic
field being there now I want to measure
that electron so I very quickly turn on
a very large magnetic field how do you
do that if it's an electromagnet it's
very easy you flip a switch and all of a
sudden there's a large electric field
sorry magnetic field pointing upward and
if that electric APEC's if that magnetic
field is large enough it will very
quickly cause the electron to radiate
okay so I would say no we want to be
thinking about turning on the other
field to do the measurement or to do the
preparation yeah is it possible to
prepare facing south
and then put it into the kinetic fuel
system position then the outcome is
getting long that's right if you start
you start turning over the whole device
you start with South in the bottom where
South belongs and north in the top when
North belongs then the electron will
point down eventually now you remove the
magnetic field okay you remove the
magnetic field or suddenly reverse just
we just turn off the magnet and reverse
the polarity you can do that by
reversing the current in the
electromagnet so that suddenly the South
Pole is on top and the North Pole is on
the bottom the electron was down in a
very short amount of time it'll flip up
and give off a photon was that the
question
and then the probability of that is one
yeah the probability that it will give
off yes in that circumstance the
probability that it will give off a
photon is one if on the other hand this
weren't perfectly aligned and you're at
some caddywhompus angle then the
probability would be less than one and
it's those probabilities which
constitute the experimental experience
or somehow I must get a charge out there
no it doesn't get electrically charged
it has electric charge turning on
turning on the electric current going
through these magnets you'll have to do
a little more you have to put a little
more energy into the magnet because the
because the electron is there in other
words originally the energy comes from
the energy that you are that you used to
turn on the magnetic field one more
in case of the electron actually emits a
photon that's the demon sir what happens
in that transition well the point yeah I
mean that's the language is probably
wrong here's what I can tell you if you
make the magnetic field sufficiently
large the electron will very quickly
emit in a photon now the correct answer
in general is that the photon will be
emitted at a more or less random time in
the same way that a radioactive atom
will will decay at the case with a
half-life okay it decays with a
half-life so if you put the electron
into the magnetic field in the wrong
direction it will with a certain
half-life the K the K means give off a
photon and write itself in the other
direction but if you make the magnetic
field large enough that half-life will
be very short and so it will very
suddenly flip okay during the transition
when it's transitioning
one of the things we've learned in
quantum mechanics is to ask questions
only if we know how to make the
measurement if you can tell me in detail
how to measure when the when the
electron emits its photon then we can
try to answer it I would say that's one
of these questions that is you're not
supposed to answer there's a thing
called the energy time uncertainty
principle and if you know the energy of
the electron you you're uncertain about
the time but let's let's come to
uncertainty principles later it's a good
question you have like a million
electron you can edit in the intensity
of the light tip if you can measure the
intensity of the light going off for any
given photon emitted at a random bar if
you know how many electrons there are
MSD white world or capital yes but you
can't say with any given on
boring we didn't give an electron we
Katie what right okay that's a is that
more energy system the more
that blew the piggy you making magnetic
field more energy you put in more
quickly it will that it will right
absolutely absolutely more quickly in
the sense of a smaller half-life right
okay so first of all we're dealing with
a theory that only has problem that has
a probabilistic description and we will
see ultimately that there is really
probably there's probably no way around
the fact that the description has to be
probabilistic at least at some level the
mathematics of the state space of the of
the concept of a state the state is
different in quantum mechanics it's
clearly different if this were clearly
different it's a system with only two
states you think but then again it seems
to be able to be oriented in any
direction the mathematics of quantum
mechanics and the states are in
particular the states of a quantum bit
are not the mathematics of a set of two
points they're not the boolean
mathematics of a set of two points this
thing which describes the mathematics
describes a quantum state is a vector
space now I use vector in a different
sense it is no longer an arrow in
ordinary space it is a mathematical
abstract vector space whose character
you'll come to understand if you persist
in the
and persist at it a little bit you will
begin to understand what this vector
space is and how it characterizes the
possible configurations or the possible
states of an electron and how it can be
consistent with this fact here okay I'm
going to spend a little bit of time now
just doing some abstract mathematics
very abstract mathematics and then we'll
seek to interpret it and to interpret
the state of the electron I'm going to
tell you what a linear vector space is
what a vector space is a vector space is
a collection of objects and here are the
rules for an abstract vector space
though as I said do not confuse this
with the pointer that that is a vector
in ordinary space this is just an
abstract completely abstract concept
first of all the vector is an object and
we'll label it like that it's an object
with a set of rules a set it's a
collection of objects it's a collection
of objects with a rule
first of all a rule that any vector can
be multiplied by a constant to get a new
vector this gives a new vector we could
call it let's call it a prime so there's
a concept of multiplication by a
constant now first of all let me tell
you that the constants we're going to be
talking about are complex numbers not
real numbers anybody here not familiar
with the concept of a complex number if
so raise your hand and be humiliated
okay all right now if you really don't
know what a complex now it may be that
you know it but it by another word now
if you really don't know about complex
numbers look them up oh because you're
going to need them
alright a complex remember this this
number I I is the square root of -1 now
-1 has no number that's through school
or there's no number ordinary number
whose square whose square is minus 1 so
there is no square root of minus 1 any
number times itself is always positive
right 3 times 3 is 9 minus 3 times minus
3 is also 9 all right but mathematicians
many many many years ago invented the
abstract idea of an imaginary number
they called an imaginary and said let it
be that I squared is equal to minus 1
invent the new number okay we know how
to use those numbers I'm not going to
I'm not going to spend any time at it
whoever raised a hand are they familiar
with I equals the square root of -1 yes
all right now you can have complex
numbers complex numbers or what happens
if you take two two real numbers
ordinary numbers let's call it a and B
different a plus I B in other words if
you add a real number to an imaginary
number you get a complex number that's
the whole definition of a complex number
you can multiply complex numbers and all
you have to remember you use the
ordinary rules of arithmetic except you
have to remember that I squared is minus
1 so for example if you're going to well
as an exercise you can square this
what's the square of a plus IB I won't
tell you
go work it out all right so that's a
complex number often character often
written is Z sometimes either you can
use any letter that you like but it's a
complex number with both a real part
than an imaginary part another concept
is the complex conjugate this is very
important you'll need it all right and
it's very simple it's a minus IB is the
complex conjugate of Z so if you take a
real no if you take a complex number and
you change the sign of the imaginary
part that's called the complex conjugate
of the number the complex conjugate of
the complex conjugate gives you back the
original number that these are important
mathematical concepts they're very
elementary let me give you an example
supposing you multiply Z star by Z what
is that that's a or Z times Z star it
doesn't matter either way it's a plus I
B times a minus I B let's see what we
get just ordinary multiplication we open
up the brackets here we get a times a
which is a squared we get a times IB
with a minus sign minus I a B plus I a B
from this one times this one and then
what about IB times IB what does IB
times IB give minus B squared but
there's a minus sign here already so
it's minus I times I times B and so that
gives plus B squared all together we get
a squared plus B squared these pieces
cancel so that's an example of using
common mean that's an example now we're
not using it for anything it's just an
example of a definition and then using
the definition of complex arithmetic to
calculate what Z star Z is notice that Z
star Z is always real and it's always
positive it's always real and positive a
squared a and B are real numbers a
squared + B squared are both positive so
Z star Z is a real number and it's
positive it's lot of more or less is the
magnitude of the come of the of a
complex number all right so first of all
for the kind of vector spaces we're
going to be thinking about they're
called complex vector spaces and one of
the rules of one of the operations that
exists in the complex vector space is
multiplication by a complex number now a
complex number includes real numbers
incidentally so you can see could be 2
or it could be I or it could be 2 plus I
or anything like that there's a notion
if there's a vector you may multiply it
by a constant and you get a new vector
that's the first operation and there's
only one other operation that's of
interest to us it's adding vectors
there's a rule for adding vectors or
assume there's a rule for adding vectors
so if I have two vectors a and B I can
construct an vector called a plus B and
that's some new vector which I guess we
can call C but C is a different C that
appears here this C stood for constant
this C just stands for a new vector
which is a plus B so every pair of
vectors you can add them and I'm going
to show you I'm going to show you some
less abstract
examples but first of all the simplest
example of a vector space like this is
just the complex numbers themselves the
ordinary complex numbers allow you to
multiply any complex number by another
complex number in particular a constant
particular kind of complex number and it
allows you to add complex numbers so
just complex numbers by themselves or a
vector space a complex vector space
that's the simplest example
but let me show you another example and
the other example is something we talked
about last time which we called column
vectors just represent an abstract
quantity by a set of components all the
components are themselves complex
numbers so for every vector really what
that vector is standing for I write
equal signs I probably shouldn't write
equals mathematicians would have a
stroke if I wrote equals their is
represented by a column vector the
column vector has entries and it's just
a table of numbers but it's a table of
complex numbers all right the table of
complex numbers supposing you want to
multiply that column vector here by a
constant the rule is very simple
multiply every entry by that constant so
C times AE is represented by ca1 ca2 ca3
we just multiply all the components by
the same number that's multiplication by
a constant how do we add two vectors
together let's suppose we have two
vectors a and B a is represented by the
column whose entries are a 1 a 2 a 3 B
is represented by B 1 B 2 B 3 well these
aren't with the bays and B's are just
numbers and when we add them we just get
a third column vector whose entries are
a 1 plus B 1 a 2 plus B 2 a 3 plus B 3
so column vectors are an example of a
vector space and they are the basic
example that we will use over and over
again as I said mathematicians would
have a stroke if I call the
vectors that would say the columns
represent vectors and you would call
these the components or a set of
components of a vector okay um that's
the idea of an abstract vector space the
very strange thing is that the states of
a quantum system in particular a quantum
bit Oh incidentally you're not
restricted to three this is a particular
case this is a three dimensional vector
space all right we could have a two
dimensional vector space that's actually
going to be more interesting to us for
the moment a two dimensional vector
space just has two entries that's the
next simplest thing if you like to the
numbers the next simplest vector space
is a two dimensional vector space and
there's a three dimensional vector space
and a four dimensional vector space and
so forth and they will make sense okay
that's you'll get used to this sooner or
later you'll you'll start thinking in
terms of abstract vector spaces if you
pursue this subject there's no way to
learn quantum mechanics honestly and
correctly without going through this
mathematics so it's it's absolutely
essential now John if we were talking
about the simplest vector space just
complex numbers then every complex
number has its complex conjugate that
means that there is a second vector
space which is the space of the complex
conjugate numbers right that the concept
of complex conjugation is an important
concept and it also exists for other
vector spaces all you have to do
basically is write the complex conjugate
of the entries but a rule when you're
writing the complex conjugate of a
vector I want to write the complex
conjugate of the vector AE you draw it
the other way this way that stands for
the complex conjugate
it of the vector a and furthermore you
represent it by a row vector the
components of the row vector are the
complex conjugates a 1 star a 2 star so
whenever you see a row vector always
think of it as the complex conjugate of
the corresponding of a corresponding
column vector if I tell you this are a
row vector a which is in correspondence
with a column vector a II always
remember that there's a complex
conjugation operation this is the basic
idea of a complex vector space written
out in components everybody happy with
that anybody those no asterisks that the
a
no usually that's right it that that's
right the the notation does not put a
star over here but do you remember that
the star is implicit in turning the
symbol backward now I'll remind you this
symbol is called the ket now the symbol
is called a bra this symbol is called a
ket do I have it right
I don't another one of them is a bra one
of them is a ket but it doesn't matter
it's completely symmetric between the
two remember that the complex conjugate
of a complex conjugate is the original
thing so that's that's the notion of a
complex vector space and finally not
finally but we want to put the pieces
together you can multiply two vectors
the product it's called we've discussed
this before I realize I'm not getting
senile I know we're talked about this
before but we need we really need to do
it right now there's the concept of the
inner product of two vectors the inner
product of two vectors the easiest way
for me to describe it is in terms of
components I don't want to spend a lot
of time giving you the most abstract
definition are there many mathematicians
in the audience plug you ears just just
just just plug them up and go all right
um
they actually mathematicians also use
components but um I think anyway the
next concept is the concept of the
product of two vectors but it's always
and it's the inner product of the two
vectors and the concept is really the
product of a vector with the complex
conjugate of another vector it's very
much like multiplying a complex number
by the complex by a complex number by
the complex conjugate of another number
could be the same number could be
another number so I'm going to give you
the rule
the rule I'm going to tell you in terms
of components okay here's the rule if I
want the inner product between the
vector B and the vector AE is written
like that it's got a bra ket that's a
bracket okay that's where the term bra
ket came from half a brow half a bracket
as a bra the other half of a vector is a
cat and again I forget which one is
which this is the cat right yeah that's
the cat this one's the bra okay good
good
the rule is you take the two that you
take the two vectors the B vector is a
row vector and you're right b1 star b2
star that's the representation of the B
vector and the representation of the a
vector is a 1 a 2 you do not star it and
the inner product between them this
product has gotten by multiplying the
first component of B with the first
component of a eb1 star a 1 plus B 2
star a 2 first first row with first
sorry first entry here with first entry
here plus second entry here second entry
here supposing for example okay
everybody that's that's the basic
concept of the inner product it's just
like multiplying two numbers together
except we get a term for each for each
entry one entry in the two entry for
example if we take the inner product of
a vector with itself let's take a with
AE the inner product of a vector with
itself as the form a 1 star a 1 plus a 2
star a 2 notice one thing about this a
number of times its complex conjugate is
first of all positive and second of all
real well it couldn't hardly be positive
if it weren't real it's a positive
number so the sum so the inner product
of a complex vector with itself is
always a real positive number
it can be thought of as a kind of size
of a vector it's actually the square of
the size of the vector if you like you
can think of it as a square of the size
of the vector the length of the vector
it measures it measures the magnitude of
the vector so this operation of inner
product is absolutely essential as we'll
see to the interpretation and it's
complex vectors like this which
represent the states of a quantum bit
let me just digress when you stop doing
mathematics for a minute and talk about
the quantum bit again the quantum bit
could be pointing straight up we could
invent a symbol for the state for the
configuration of the electron pointing
up let's call it we could either we
could call it up or we could call it a
little vector up or we could just call
it plus I think I'll just call it plus
to indicate that it's pointing upward or
we can have an electron which is
pointing down now remember when we go to
measure the electron we either find that
it's up or down and nothing in between
and that we can identify with the vector
minus just an abstract notation this
stands for the state of an electron
pointing up this stands for the state of
an electron pointing down now in
classical physics we would never under
any circumstances think of adding these
two vectors or multiplying them by
numbers we would just say this means
electron and up this means electron down
in quantum physics the general state of
an electron or an electron spin is a
vector in a vector space which we could
write
a plus x plus plus a minus x minus in
other words it's a two-dimensional
vector space we could also represent it
by a plus a minus and he is the rule the
rule that's so there are some
coefficients that we can add them
together with and here's the meaning of
those coefficients or at least a partial
meaning of those coefficients a plus
star a plus is the probability that we
find the electron up
remember it's positive it's positive and
it's real a star times a is positive and
it's real and it's the magnitude of the
or the square of the magnitude of the
coefficient of the up configuration and
then there's the down configuration the
probability of finding the electron down
is a minus times a star minus that's the
probability to find it down that's the
interpretation or that's part of the
interpretation just to give you some
orientation where we're going the
quantum state of that electron which
when we measure it we find with a
probabilistic distribution is either up
or down and nothing in between that's
represented by saying the electron when
it's pointing in some funny angle is
given by a complex vector complex vector
space which can either be represented
abstractly like this it can be
represented concretely as a column
vector and the square or magnitude of
the square of the entries here are
simply the probabilities to find it up
or down now presumably probabilities add
to one so one of the rules about quantum
mechanics
is that the vectors that represent that
we have a vector space of some kind an
abstract vector space but the vectors
which actually represent the physical
states of a system are the word is
normalized normalized means that the sum
of the probabilities is one so a plus
star a plus plus a minus star a minus
should be set equal to one this is like
considering only vectors of unit length
that doesn't mean that in the vector
space itself there aren't other vectors
of other magnitude there are but the
physical states of a quantum system have
to be normalized which is the same thing
as setting the sums of the probabilities
to one so normalized vectors in the
vector space represent the states of a
quantum system now that's a very
abstract concept why do we get driven to
such very abstract concepts why can't we
visualize this the same way we visualize
classical physics well it's because we
don't have the wiring and we have to
rewire ourselves and we have to rewire
ourselves to learn to think about the
quantum states of a system being an
abstract vector space once you get this
idea of an abstract vector space and how
it fits together with the states of a
system then you're flying and you can
understand all of quantum mechanics so
any questions about this the entries the
coefficients or equivalently the
components of the vector when you square
them or better yet when you multiply
them by their own complex conjugate give
you the probabilities for the two
possibilities yeah that represents a
quantum state if a star a a in fact we
can say it this way the inner product of
a with itself that's given by a star a
plus star
a plus plus a minus star a - that should
be one so legitimate quantum states
should have inner product with
themselves which is equal to one and
that's just a statement if it's that's
just a statement that the sums of the
probabilities of all the probabilities
where is very for all those like column
vector a plus B minus o plus and minus
are now just to indicate that one of
them corresponds to spin up and the
other corresponds that has been down and
we could have called them eight when we
could have given them different names I
could have called them a up and a down
or I could have called them a1 and a2
they do have they do have they are the
coefficients of the ket plus and the ket
- okay so let's go back a step back a
step what about the ket plus how should
we represent that in some basis let's
well at the moment I don't want to
discuss the the ambiguity of in basis
vectors will come to that but for the
moment we have a basis the Moriya but
you don't know I'm talking about this
vector will be represented by one zero
okay it'll never be represented by a 1
in the upper place and a zero in the
lower place what about the - cat the -
cat is represented by a 0 and a 1 this
is just some arbitrary correspondence
okay now then if I multiply this by a
plus the numerical constant a plus then
we have to multiply this by a plus we
don't have to multiply 0 plus a plus
because 0 times anything is 0 if we
multiply this by a minus then this
becomes a minus here and if we add them
together
a plus x the plus cat plus a minus times
the minus cat we just add these together
and we get adding them gives us a plus a
minus okay
does that answer the question that was
asked okay so yes we said certainly the
plus and minus notation instead of one
and two here I used 1 & 2 they're just
labels they're just labels 1 & 2 is just
a label to label the two entries I could
have used up and down I could have used
Joe and Pete I could have used anything
I want to label them here I'm using plus
and minus the two possibilities for the
orientation of the electron of the
electron or of the quantum bit I'm
labeling them by plus and minus good
okay so now we have a a basic concept of
a vector space the inner product
- Jerry get over to our come here just -
okay reminders kept mine is one nice no
the - ket is not minus 1 times the plus
ket no no no no no no no oh yeah this
matter yes
yeah you're asking you're asking whether
the whether this object makes sense yes
you're allowed to take any vector and
multiply it by any complex number in
particular a complex number is minus 1
in fact but this but this is not it is
not the same as - right this has a fist
okay let's let's make that clear the -
here does not mean that it's - the +
vector it's just a label no more than 8
then the then the a 2 means twice a 1
is that the popular altruistic estate
so - plus cat and cat both represent
state where you have probably one
trusted yes that's correct that's
correct
oh no the line is candid probability
want to the highness state wait wait
this cat here has probability one in the
plus side but so I love minus sign we
also have which one per corner if we
remove them I - that's right that's
right
both of these that's right absolutely
absolutely we're gonna come to that
very good very good very good very good
well you're you're pointing out
something that I was about to come to in
a moment I'll tell it to you right now
well okay if I multiply it by any
complex number of magnitude one its ass
that's right that's correct that's
correct so physically we would not
distinguish this state from from this
state I won't write equals because in
the mathematical vector space they're
not equal but they represent the same
physics however however when I add them
a plus and minus a minus are not the
same that is a different state all right
that is a different state with a minus
sign here but we'll come to that we'll
come to that it was something I was
going to talk about but not yet I want
you to digest just the idea that the
components of these abstract vectors
when squared correspond to probabilities
and they make physical sense to tank
Jinxy - Ken - the broth off are those
two together yes you're gone - is my
head so red spots let's so it's coming I
think you're asking whether it makes
sense to take the cat vector plus and
consider what I'll call its conjugate
which is the bra the bra vector plus in
this case the there's no change because
Z well we can accept that you would
write it as a row right what about the
in a proton is they'll change that's
right in this case in this case right
the course one is a real number we don't
have two complex conjugated okay so
here's a here's a little exercise what's
the inner product of the Plus vector
with itself one one because it's just
multiplying 1 0 times 1 0 1 times 1 is 1
so this is 1 what about - - also equal
to 1 what about the inner product of
plus with -
let's just check that for those who
don't see it so quickly let's just check
it the plus bra is one zero the - ket is
0-1 all right so we multiply them
together we get 1 times 0 plus 0 times 1
which is all together 0 what about -
plus also 0 what's the word for two
vectors whose inner product is 0 both
agonal orthogonal they're called
orthogonal vectors so the two vectors
representing the two distinct states of
the electron one up and one down are two
orthogonal vectors in a linear vector
space of states a linear vector space of
states okay that's the basic set up our
and the coefficients that appear there
they're squared magnitudes are the
probabilities for the two configurations
the probability for up and for down now
as you can see there are more possible
physical states than just up and down
there are all the linear combinations
it's the linear combinations of them
that correspond to the electron point
there having been prepared in different
directions so in other words an
arbitrary combination like this with a
plus and a minus there when this is not
1 in 0 1 0 and 1 correspond when you
consider all the possible complex
numbers to the different directions that
you might have prepared the electron but
still all there is is up and down and
the probabilities for up and down so a
state for example let me give you an
example
a vector a vector let's write one in
both and both slots that's not allowed
why isn't that allowed probably doesn't
add to one alright so the probability
would add to 2 here 1 squared plus 1
squares do we have to divide it by
square root of 2 now each of the
probabilities is 1/2 and they add up to
1 parentheses where you're right
I make the right to column
that's a state with equal probability
namely probability 1/2 to find the
electron up and now this one has
probability 1/2 to find the electron
down there are more states than just up
and down and in fact this one
corresponds to what you would create if
you created the electron pointing in the
horizontal direction if with a magnetic
field in the horizontal direction you
froze the electron let's take a break
if you froze the electron the place with
a magnetic field in the horizontal
direction in the horizontal plane one of
the possibilities would be this state
here which would have half a probability
of being up and half a probability of
being down half the probability would be
up and half the probability being down
actually corresponds to some
configuration where the electron is
lying somewheres in the in the
horizontal plane so we have plenty of
vectors around with all kinds of complex
numbers out of which we can build and
we'll see that we can do this we can
build these the space of electrons which
in some sense of pointing in any
direction but whenever we measure them
all we get is up or down with
probabilities that are governed by these
coefficients let's take a break for 7
minutes 7 or 7 minutes and 30 seconds
all right now more than one person is
probably a little bit confused about the
two notions of vectors one is having to
do with directionality in ordinary space
and one having to do with this abstract
concept and this notion of components of
vectors labeling upstate and downstate
question is what's the connection
between the notion of directionality in
space and these vectors here now what I
want to say first of all is they are not
simply related they are related but not
simply related for example
how many components does a vector have
an ordinary vector three on and then and
they're real numbers right XY and Z
they're all real numbers these vectors
have two components and they're complex
numbers and that means how many how many
real numbers does it take to describe
one of them for all right so they're not
the same thing but there must be some
connection we're not going to do that
connection just yet
but we will come to it next concept
which we already went into a little last
time is the concept of a matrix
is right
okay it's an experimental question from
the fact that there were only two
possible answers to the way or that when
you do this experiment on the electron
you either get that it's up or down and
nothing in between that tells you that
there are two possibilities and it tells
you that you should be dealing with a
2-dimensional vector space all
two-dimensional complex vector spaces
are mathematically the same so they're
all the same a two-dimensional complex
vector space is a two-dimensional
complex vector space there's no there's
not more than one of them mathematically
so ah so you count up the number of
possibilities somebody asked me before
if I had to spin one particle instead of
a spin 1/2 particle which is what an
electron is how many components would
there be then there would be three but
it's an experimental question how many
possibilities are there how many states
are there how many how many distinct
possibilities are there and in the case
of the electron spin in the case of the
spin of the electron there are two
possibilities and so it's a two
dimensional vector space and they're all
the same there's no there's no
distinction between different two
dimensional vector spaces other than the
fact that we could consider the real or
complex vector spaces okay let's let's
move on to the concept to the abstract
concept of a linear operator or the
concrete concept of a matrix let me tell
you where we're going we've talked about
States but we haven't talked about the
things that you actually measure the
things that you measure or that you can
measure are called the observables the
observables of a system are the things
that you can measure and get answers for
position of an electron isn't observable
but we're not doing anything as
complicated as that as that
if we were to label the up and the down
state as plus and minus we could invent
an observable which would have two
possible values it could either be plus
plus one or minus one and it would be an
observable that we could measure if the
electrons up we will assign it the
number plus one if it's down we'll
assign it the number minus one also
called an observable anything that we
can measure that has a numerical value
numerical value means a real number
anything that we can measure that when
that when the measurement is recorded
then it gives rise to a number in
numerical number is called an observable
so as I said in the case of the electron
spin if we measure the if we measure the
whether it's up or down we could assign
up the number plus one and down the
number minus one and in that way have an
observable which whose numerical value
when we measure it is either plus 1 or
minus 1 let me talk about before talking
about observables in quantum mechanics
let's talk about observables for a
minute in classical mechanics including
classical theory in classical theory the
states of a system are just a set of
states which we represented by points
how many you have 1 2 3 4 5 6 these
could be the six possibilities for
throwing a dice a by a single die the 1
2 3 4 5 6 this is and we could assign
some numbers to each one of these points
we could call we could label this 1 1 2
3 4 5 6 we throw the die and we look at
it that's the measurement we throw the
die and we look at it and we get an
answer the answer is either 1 2 3 4 5 or
that measurement is the measure
than above an observable and it's an
observable which has six possible
answers there are other observables that
we could concoct for example we could
concoct an observable which is zero
everywhere except at one value one zero
zero zero zero zero now this means that
if we flip the die and we get a 1 we
assign the number 1 to the observable if
we get any other number we assign the
value 0 to then it could be observable
so there are many observables that you
can make and basically they correspond
to any functions of these points any
functions of these points assign any
function to the points function points
meaning assign any numbers you like to
these points real numbers and then when
you flip the die and you see what comes
up you say the value of the observable
is whatever the numerical value of that
observable was when you flip it back
there are many many observables that you
can think about in this in this simple
system but they're all rather trivial I
mean they just correspond to to the
basic question of whether the die is 1 2
3 4 5 or 6 um it's interesting just not
because yes it is interesting to define
the observable as a function of which
state we're talking about F sub n n here
represents which of these states were
talking about and F is a function which
could be any number for each of these
states
that's called an observable when you
flip a die you look at what you get and
you assign the number F
the particular state F sub one F sub two
of through F sub six that's called an
observable and that's a it's a sort of
overkill concept in this classical
situation here but but let's continue
now let us suppose it for one reason or
another in classical physics we haven't
been very careful in doing our classical
physics measurements and so forth and we
don't know exactly what state the system
is in all we know is some probabilities
for example we may have a loaded die a
loaded die which is an unfair die like
the kind the dirty gamblers use and you
flip it and it lands on the table there
may be a probability distribution for
different values of the one two three
four five or six let's label that P sub
n also that's the probability the a
priori probability let's say that when
you flip the die you get the nth state
then what is the average if you flip the
die many many times and each time you
measure F you can flip it many many
times you measure F what is the average
value of F after many many many
identical experiments okay the answer
anybody know well the answer for the
average value of F or we're assuming of
course that the sum of the piece of ends
is 1 in other words the sum of the
probabilities of 1 the average value of
F is the sum of all the possibilities of
the probability for the nth power for
the nth the configuration times the
value that the function has in the nth
configuration so what you do is you add
up all the configurations weighted
according to their probability weight
them according to their probability for
example if all the proper all the
probabilities are equal all right then
you just add up the F sub ends if
they're all equal incidentally they're
not one there the 1 over N because
they're 1 over the number 1 over 6 in
this case but this is the average over
many many let's let's take an example
let's do a coin a simple coin or up or
down heads or tails let's say there's
the probability for heads and we're
going to call heads Plus is the
probability for heads which is P plus
there's the probability for tails which
is P minus alright if we have heads we
assign the number plus 1 if we have
tails we assign the number minus 1 what
is the probability for that observable
which is either plus 1 or minus 1 it's P
plus the probability for plus minus the
probability for minus because every time
you get a minus you give it a value
minus 1 every time in other words every
time you get a tail you give it a sauna
minus 1 every time you get a head you
give it a plus 1 the average is P plus
minus P minus the difference between the
probability of head and tail is the
average of the heads Nisour the tails
nests so this basic formula here
which is just the most elementary
formula of probability of the notion of
an average that you average over all the
possibilities weighing it with the value
of the quantity the observable whose
average you're taking and you weigh it
according to the probability of that
particular configuration and that's the
average value of an experiment which
consists of many many repeated
experiments what's that
expected value sometimes called the
expected I sometimes called the
expectation value sometimes called the
average value and and that's what we're
going to be interested in we're going to
be interested in the average values of
things that we can measure the average
values of observables now I what I
haven't told you is how you represent
observables in quantum mechanics and the
representation of observables in quantum
mechanics is more intricate and
complicated than just saying we assign
to each state a numerical value that we
call the observable value in that state
it's a more complicated concept and a
more tricky concept the notion of an
observable or measurable measurable
quantity and it's related not related
but is well related related to the
concept of a linear operator or a matrix
so for our purposes the same thing again
the mathematicians will object to me
saying a matrix is a linear operator I
don't know the other job anybody object
my saying a matrix is a linear operator
what yes courage to do this example
yeah of plus is 1 and F of minus is
minus 1 desperate they should value
though is you're off if the
probabilities are equal
yeah well I think probably is equal so
is this the expectation value ends up
being a number that is that the
underlying system is never in that state
oh that's true yeah yeah yeah right
that's why people don't like calling it
the expected value because it is the it
is a value which is very definitely not
expected so I everybody used to call it
the expectation value now that's a
little that's a little weaker than
saying the expected value then my friend
Murray gell-mann started calling it the
expected value well it ain't as you
point out the expected value is more
than that because you have to bark on
you really haven't by by N and as grown
the sums of the peas are up to one
assuming the sums of the peas add up to
one
okay but when you think of it as
dividing by the overall sample size in
this case yeah that's a piece of P is
1/2 and 1/2 that means that you
the typical person having two and a half
kids okay right so there's nothing it's
not really be expected you know you have
to guess how many kids you're going to
have you probably wouldn't get two and a
half it's a payoff in the gambling you
can actually run up a zero well you said
so it's about you get it you put the
corresponding point then this is the
average value it's by definition the
average value okay so that's right so if
I'm glad your point to this count that
if P + + P - were both 1/2 then the add
then the average value would be 0 but 0
is not a possible answer so the average
value is not the expected value there is
no expected value in this case but it
doesn't something you get something at 0
the average value it considered a lot
higher villages and self-esteem so again
it hasn't it as well as I would a
virgin's that's a lot the variance is to
Wi-Fi well I think coin we might flip it
a fair coin and I flip it I think we'll
get 1/2 times heads and F times tails
you said something about you see
something about temperature there they
are yes in the case of composting of
course it tells you that you is a 50/50
percent chance no hey Jeff yeah I told
you you put your basically completely
ignorant if you're completely ignorant
there's a 50/50 chance and and if you do
the experiment over and over with a fair
coin and you average the result the
average had better be zero because it
can't be can't be positive and it can't
be negative because equal balance on the
other hand if you have an unfair coin
let's say three quarters of the time it
comes up heads and one quarter of the
times that come the pails then the
average is what it's 3/4 minus 1/4 which
is 1/2 all right so if you have this
unfair coin which 3/4 of the time comes
ups heads one quarter comes up tails
then the average is 1/2 all right again
doesn't mean that you can measure 1/2 it
just means that that's the average value
ok a ver egde are important let me give
you one observable one kind of
observable which is special supposing I
take this special class of observables
which is one at one state F is one for
one state over here and zero for all the
others what's the average value of it
just a probability right just the
probability so if I had an observable
which I invented which was one at one
place and zero everyplace else then
there would be only one term in the sum
because F is zero for all the others and
for the one case where it's not zero we
just get P so if you knew the rules for
calculating averages you would also know
the rules for calculating for all
possible observables you would also a
we know the rule for calculating
probabilities another way to say it is
if you know how to calculate the average
value of any observable you can
reconstruct for it from it the
probability distribution the
probabilities for those for that
observable probabilities for
probabilities for different different
for the different possibilities so that
raises the question now what is the
mathematical representation of
observables and that is matrices
matrices or linear operators so let's
talk again a little bit about matrices
and we're like I don't know where I am
let's let's talk about observables or or
let's talk about matrices but first a
matrix is a thing that you can multiply
a vector with or act on a vector with it
it does something to a vector it's an
operation on a vector but it's not just
any old operation on the vector it's a
linear operation I'm not going to
explain that because we won't need to
explain it R but whatever it is call it
m m for matrix and in the abstract
notation it's a thing it's an object
which you multiply a vector by and you
get a new vector for example one simple
example is just multiplying by a complex
number multiplying by a complex number
is a operator it's a very simple
operator you just multiply the vector
and you get the amount a vector the
number 2 just takes every vector and
doubles its size okay all right but the
general make the general operators that
we're going to consider are ones which
are represented by
matrices matrices so if we have our
vector AE which we represent by a column
vector and I'm only going to write two
dimensional column vectors because
because but you'll immediately deduce
what to do if you have a few more
entries here all right we can multiply
it by a matrix and a matrix as a square
array of numbers M 1 1 m12 m21 M 2 2 and
in general these numbers are all complex
numbers in general they're all complex
numbers the A's and the MS in a complex
vector space can all be complex numbers
and the rule for matrix multiplication
which we discussed last time for
multiplying a matrix by a vector is just
if you want the top entry which you can
think of as the top row you take the top
row and you multiply it by the vector
you take the inner product of the top
row with a vector which will be M 1 1 a
1 plus M 1 2 a 2 and then I'm down here
and 2 1 a 1 plus M 2 2 a 2 so it's
another vector I have to draw a pretty
wide because I was adding some numbers
here but it's just a vector it's a
column vector with one column and it's
constructed by taking this row times the
column and this row times a column and
those are the two entries
that's it that's all in matrices are let
me give you a couple of examples a
couple of simple examples from a very
ordinary vector space a very ordinary
vector space is just the point there is
are the arrows that you can draw in the
blackboard you can multiply a vector by
in this case a real number you can
double it you can triple it you can
multiply it by minus 1 and you can add
two vectors so vectors that you draw on
the blackboard are a vector space let me
give you and they have what are their
components their components are the X
component is X is y and the vector has
an X component and a Y component so we
represent this vector by its X component
that its Y component and we could write
it in the form X component of vector Y
component of the vector of course now
I'm only doing two dimensional space
these would be real numbers on the
blackboard there wouldn't be complex
numbers and this would be a two real
dimensional vector space now let's think
about some operations the first
interesting operation which is the most
easy is to stretch the vector space for
example multiply every vector by 2 ok
multiply of every vector by 2 will sort
of magnify the whole space by a factor
of 2 any vector will get stretched out
to twice its original length that's all
what happens here is the matrix that
represents that operation it's just the
diagonal matrix two two diagonal means
that its entries are along the diagonal
there are two diagonals the matrix this
is called the principal diagonal I think
if I remember the other one is called
the unprincipled I agonal I don't know
what it's called
Wow the good diagonal and the bad
diagonal this one is the bad diagonal
all right let's just calculate what we
get all right in the upper entry we get
two times VX plus zero so the upper
entry just becomes two VX
the lower entry we get two times V Y so
as advertised this is the operator which
simply doubles the length of every
vector all right very easy
here's more almost similar a similar
thing but supposing I just wanted to
double the Y component what would that
do to the vector space it would take
every vector and stretch out its y
component by a factor of two without
stretching out its X component so it
would be a stretch in the Y direction by
a factor of two but no stretch in the X
direction how would we represent that
okay again a diagonal with a 1 here in
the X place in the X X and the YY place
the fact that - let's check it 1 times V
X gives us VX 2 times V y gives us twice
V Y so that's a stretching of the vector
space in the in the in the Y direction
likewise we could put the 2 here and the
1 here that would be a stretching of the
vector space which stretches it out in
this direction one or two more well it's
just a these are these are very easy
examples so far they've only involved
diagonal matrices let me give you
another one the the matrix which
corresponds to rotating every vector by
90 degrees take any vector and rotate it
by 90 degrees in other words this is the
operation which rotates the plane by 90
degrees I'll tell you what it is and
then we'll check and see if we can see
why it's off diagonal or
1 1 1 -1 excuse me oh let's do this one
first let's do what this is before I do
the rotation let's do this let's see
what this does this takes zero times V X
1 times V Y it interchanges V Y and V X
interchanges we want in V X anybody see
geometrically what that corresponds to a
reflection it's a reflection of the
vector space about this diagonal takes
every vector and reflect it about that
diagonal just flips it about that
diagonal that's this matrix
here's another matrix where you put a
minus 1 down here what does this give
this gives V Y minus V X V Y minus V X
ok it interchanges the x and y but then
throws in a minus sign for one of them
that is an operation I'm going to leave
it to you to prove because we don't have
time but I'm going to tell you what this
does it rotates the vector space by 90
degrees Oh does it go the other way
it's an easy way to see all this wood
but you eat all the starry sky right
here every direction he so here
rotates rotates every type of a 90
degree the microphone what's that
rotating the one rivet around the x and
y component s component is going into -
right so what I kept pointing in the X
directions going into - the vectors for
you so which resources they were
rotating by 90 degrees in the o clock
rotate clockwise yeah that's what I drew
here yeah yeah yeah it rotates vector by
90 degrees so you see what matrices
correspond to is they correspond to a
transformations of the vector space
stretching's rotations more complicated
kinds of things another example would be
a shear shear this is interesting to try
to work out the matrix that corresponds
to a shear motion let me tell you what a
shear motion is or a sheer motion ish a
shear motion takes every vector well it
it's super boy slides stuff this way
okay so it slides you to the right by an
amount proportional to how high you are
it takes every point and shifts it to
the right by an amount proportional to
how high you are there's a matrix that
describes that motion the forms the
plane tilts this axis over is what it
does I'm not going to write that one out
I'll see if you can find it the next
time I'll tell you what the answer is
for a for shear motion but in general
matrices correspond to transformations
special transformations not all
transformations are represented as
matrices these are the linear
transformations to be specific but these
are the ones we're going to be
interested in and we're going to be
interested in a special class of them
now this is very abstract and for the
moment you will not see why it is just
definition
but I got to give you some mathematics
and then interspersed it with some
physics I'm going to give you the
mathematics and today and next time I'm
going to show you what the point is
there's a notion of a hermitian matrix
the notion of a hermitian matrix the
notion of an hermitian matrix is
corresponds to the notion of a real
number it's a kind of concept of reality
versus imaginary but it's not that
doesn't mean that the entries are all
real what it means is that if you take
take an element of the matrix mije
that's and that's some element of the
matrix it could be some big matrix I
don't know how big it is and it's
somewhere over here and then there's m
ji m ji is the reflected matrix element
if this is m1 to be over here and then m
to 1 would be over here M 3 5 might be
over here M 5 3 would be over here so
interchanging rows and columns is a kind
of reflection of the matrix about the
diagonal here a hermitian matrix is one
that if you reflect it complex
conjugates
in other words m IJ is equal to m ji
star if this matrix was just a number
let's just take a case of numbers and I
tell you I have a number which is equal
to its own complex conjugate what does
that tell you about the number that it's
real then it has no imaginary part all
right now for a matrix that's not what
it says it doesn't say that the entries
are real but it's a kind of reality
property let me give you some examples
of matrices one which is hermitian
everybody know how to spell hermitian
h ER m ay es h un hermit ian heard HP
RMIT I ya know
you say some people hungry for me hi my
name's with eer her mom is a kind of
little know each polynomials okay in
other words when you flip it you get the
complex conjugate here is some example
oh oh that says one thing it says that
diagonal elements are real because m11
what does it say that says M 1 1 is M
star 1 1 if you flip the rows and
columns on the diagonal you get the same
answer for example I equals 1 J equals 1
M 1 1 equals M 1 1 star so first of all
it says the diagonal elements are real
real numbers here it's 7 and 3 but then
it says that the off diagonal elements
are complex conjugates of each other so
here's a matrix for example that is not
hermitian 4 and to let not hermitian
because 2 is not the complex conjugate
of 4 all right this is hermitian 4 is
the complex conjugate of 4 so if a
matrix is real and it's hermitian it's
also symmetric but here's another one
which is hermitian 4 + I + 4 - I 4 plus
I is the complex conjugate of 4 minus I
so this is the notion of a hermitian
matrix and now I'm going to tell you
that we're going to find next time we're
going to postulate next time that
hermitian matrices are the quantum
version of observables
a classical version of observables
functions of the the state points
they're the quantum version of of
observable hermitian operator which
means of our mission matrix for the
moment that's what we're going yeah what
you'd like to do is like the get this
vector with that matrix and it's a state
of the electron system and well the sum
of the probabilities is 1 is this enough
so that you can get or listen no when
you kick it when you kick an electron
you want to kick it with a unitary
operator mission operator what's that oh
I'll tell you this what I did what a
unitary operator is one which doesn't
change the length of any vector which is
what I think what you were asking about
right right
hermitian operator does not have that
property in general so a unitary matrix
is one which doesn't change the length
and it's it's the result of an operation
that you actually do to the electron you
kick it you hit it you do something to
it I'll tell you very quickly now well
no I won't bother telling you because
we'll get into it next time matrices or
more generally linear linear operators
are the basic quantum concept of the
observable the thing that you can
measure and we're going to then discuss
what kind of matrices correspond to the
Z component the up-down component of the
spin what kind correspond to the X
component of the spin what kind
correspond to the Y component what kind
of observable what kind of matrix
corresponds to the component of the spin
along some arbitrary direction and so
we're going to see then that there's a
connection between these vectors
matrices and so forth and real
directions of space but that's going to
take some time it'll take some some
little more pieces without all of this
there's no way that you can understand
honestly what entanglement is or bells
in
qualities mean what what the basic setup
of quantum mechanics is so it's more
mathematical of to be able to teach this
without all this mathematics but I can't
there's no way so you want honestly you
want it correctly you want the the basic
ingredients that go into quantum
mechanics we have to go through this bit
of mathematics once we're through it
hermitian operators vectors and so forth
then the rest is kind of smooth sailing
it's it's it's relatively easy stuff but
so far we've had to spend more time on
mathematics and I might've liked but
okay
the preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu